welcome everybody to voices with raviki
i'm joined with my friend nick wickelman
uh nick and i met at uh the movement
summit
uh organized by rave kelly and others
and uh we hit it off
uh uh quite significantly we've had a
couple of
i think actually three conversations
we've had so far together um and it's
been really really good
um and we're also on a panel together
and i'm really excited to have
uh nick here some of the work he's
written a book called the language of
coaching
uh it's really good uh my son keeps
picking it up and
then going through it and what is this
book and it's he's really really
uh thrilled by um and the work that nick
is doing
and um is so constant with my own so
welcome nick it's just wonderful to have
you here
john it's a true honor you know as you
said
rafe has kind of been this uh common
point
of intersection he's like hey have you
ever heard of this guy john verveiki i
think
he talks about words as well and i think
you might find him in
because it could have just absolutely
passed by
in the conversation i had with him but
so few people
look at uh words
and meaning and how we use them to
transfer meaning and make meaning
and so i'm like let me check him out and
as i told you you know
some 20 hours later i'm i felt i'd
earned the right to shoot you an email
and so far our conversations
have been great that's thank you nick i
i agree
so i i maybe you could start just by
introducing yourself a bit
like say what it is you do um and say
how that cert that sort of intersects
with you know the broader themes of you
know embodied cognition
and things like that and as you see
you've already invoked it meaning making
how it's relevant to the meeting crisis
et cetera but like where are you coming
from and how you got here
i'm i'm sure our interests my viewers
will be really interested in hearing
that story
yeah it's it's quite a um well i don't
know if it's an
odd background i think meaning is
important to everybody
so i guess all backgrounds are universal
here but
my specific journey uh has me
as a strength and conditioning coach now
so
bigger faster stronger for about the
last 17 years
as long as i have have been working
so i got my first gig at 15 years old i
was working in a gym
so rightly or wrongly that's the the
context i found myself in
and a lot of it was driven out of out of
my own personal journey
to to find myself in a way and only now
through
reflection can i understand it and what
i mean by finding myself is i never
felt and this might sound superficial to
some but i'm still working through it
i never found that the way that i
appeared on the outside
was the way that i felt on the inside so
i was a football player and a basketball
player
and so like everyone call it a body
image but for me
i wanted to do something about it and so
a lot of my
entry into the movement space
into the strength and conditioning space
was through my own journey of
of yes losing weight but i think
gaining strength in in the control
in the discipline that came along with
it and so
there was a number of key players when i
was in in high school let's say
starting this journey but one of them
his name is rudy
and he was a strength conditioning coach
who worked at costco
during the day and on his own back
opened up the gym every day at 2 30
and he would come in he literally john
would ride up pretty much the same
program
on the board every day but that wasn't
the real value he brought he started
to teach you how to be a person
alongside of physically preparing to be
a player
and again i could only fully appreciate
this as i grew towards
adulthood and so rudy taught me that
through movement i could
develop the whole person and again i
would not have used
those words even in college but i think
emotionally
that's what i was drawn to and so fast
forward
i i got into the strength and
conditioning space
ultimately as a context but my i would
say my deeper
purpose is to help people in the same
way
that i had been helped and thus it was a
physical
path but very much so it has deeper
psychological meaning within it and i
reflect on that journey
and the journey i still feel that i'm on
from there and so that just kind of
gives you a sense of if you would
how it all started now fast forward to
today
i primarily work in professional sport
and so
some might even look at what i do say
well have you actually
leveraged your your skill set your your
intrigue
to to the broadest community possible
and i would say
not yet but i still consider myself not
that we ever shift out of student
but very much so on a journey of earning
the right
to be listened to by by the world and i
honestly mean that and so for the last
15 years i was working
in nfl primarily helping athletes go
from college to the nfl via the nfl
combine
running professional education for other
strand coaches
and fitness professionals so the
transfer of knowledge
helping use words to make meaning in
both my athletes and the coaches
has always been part and parcel to what
i do
and now i find myself in dublin working
in another culture
in another sport i now work in
professional rugby in a slightly
different role more of a leadership role
a high performance type role where i
work across you know 34
amazing individuals in strength
conditioning and sports science again i
find myself
in a position that demands clarity of
communication
building shared meaning and helping
other people find meaning in their path
i do quite a bit
of consulting within individuals a lot
of my colleagues
are on hey where do i go with my career
you know strength and conditioning is
very volatile
and so that's a concern especially at
the moment in time we find ourselves
and so that let's say one level of my
journey
within that within that
language has always been important
i guess it started when my mom said you
talk too much right you're destined to
be a lawyer
or something and so she she probably
she's probably right so maybe i had
something with language but
the key thing for me the first time i
came into contact
with language and i became aware of it
that might sound really odd to many
people but think about we use
language all the time but how often do
we come
in contact with it how often can we stop
and notice it you know i'm going to put
a footnote on this comment
my wife and i likely because of our
shared interests
will always comment to each other when
we
phrase something in a way that brings
joy
whether it's metaphor or analogy and
john you talk a lot about savoring
and even though i haven't explicitly
engaged in that practice
knowingly i think very often around
language my wife and i do that and
actually
throughout our life we try to stop when
something really brings us joy
and share that with the other person and
so that's just
an interesting footnote but for me the
first time i came in contact
with language i was pretty you know
general moment i was learning to become
a personal trainer
and i was following another trainer on
the floor
and i've been following him for for
weeks now
and i was trying to understand why was
he seen
as the lead trainer why was he seen
as being somehow more skilled at
training and developing others
than maybe some of the other individuals
on the floor and
i started with the obvious place and
that was the obvious
salient things his program
well what exercises does he do how many
reps and sets
how does he understand the client's
goals
how does he document how does he make
notes all the things that i could touch
and feel
and frankly were part of my textbooks
that said
this is the knowledge necessary to be a
personal trainer and train other people
and i couldn't find the answer there
john because like well he's doing bench
press on monday
he's doing bicep curls and he's doing
all the same things
but there's something different here i
can feel it and one day i
narrowed in on his his use of language
in that he was a very clever witty guy
as
is but he always protected
the moment before the client would move
to give them one idea to give them an
idea that could be
salient that could dominate their mind
be a passenger
if you would guiding how they move i
like to call it the address and the gps
gives them that one central thought and
i'll never forget i was struck by
what otherwise was a basic moment in
time
and i never i'll never forget a day or
so later i went to another kind of
senior mentor
and i said what this guy is doing i
don't even know if he realizes it
but one day i got to write a book called
the form within nobody's talking about
this
it's ever present we talk and
communicate all the time
and we know intuitively it makes this
profound difference
in ourselves how we think and how we use
language to think but also
how we interact with others i got to do
something about this
but you know it was one of those ideas
that i was not prepared
to action and so it was over
a decade later that these ideas started
to mature
again i started to find
the resources that had something to say
about how our words
impact thinking and how what we think
while we move ultimately impacts how we
move and anyone who's played tennis
or golf who's had the bad day out
they know the dark side of what thinking
can do while we move
right but i think we've also enjoyed the
ahas as you and i have talked about are
the light bulb
and so there's this this meshing between
thought and movement and
that starts to start to tap into this
embodiment how well they're all
connected
and that's how do i as a coach how do i
as a teacher how do i insert myself
in that loop in that process
well i'm not a puppet master i don't
have strings on their body
but i do have language i can put words
into their mind with the hopes that if
they're unpacked
they could make a meaningful difference
that ultimately in my world changes the
way they move
for the better which tends to converge
with why that person is there they are
pursuing a goal
that has a movement basis and so i'm
helping them
achieve an end as many people had helped
me achieve an end and so fast forward
now to 2016
i start writing the book 2020 the book
was published
and the book lives basically on on 15
years of curiosity
a decade of thinking and practicing with
a phd stuck in there just to make sure i
was on the right course
and four and four years of writing and
where does that bring me today today i
realize
uh and i mean today in a broader sense
not literally today
and this starts to converge on why what
you and i are talking about is so
important
i've been saying this now for years to
my wife i i i came to realize that
strength and conditioning
is not my purpose it is my context it is
my
arena to use your word john right right
i find that my my purpose i don't know
if i show you this but i have truth
tattooed on my form right right that is
quite it
and you see here that the u in the
middle is red
the red almost like blood the lifeline
of is to is to respect that truth is
still
fluid to the degree that there's
personal truth a truth that cannot be
objectively
concrete like an object there is what we
might hope there's a reality
there's a direct context or a realism as
we might get into with dreyfus and
taylor
but then there's this ever search for
personal truth and so i don't think i've
shared this with you yet
but that is my core value
not above all else is what i pursue and
so
when rafe kelly says this guy john
verveiki let me watch the videos
and i start to get in there i see a
person who
is is enacting his own journey even
though you're much farther in your
journey
i if i can say this i see your pain i
see your struggle
i see your pursuit of something and that
resonates or reverberates
inside of me and what i've realized in
in these discussions and
in partnership in the broadest sense
i believe i can start to take what i've
done
and i can share it with the world i can
give it a broader platform i can do
what i know is inside of me and in the
process
better understand myself my own truth
and the meaning that i seek to make in
in
in this world and so that's where i'll
maybe end
and allow you to sharpen the
conversation from here but i think that
that gives you the journey and how we
came into contact
that was excellent nick so here here's a
place that i i think
resonates with me right away especially
with that what you just said
uh truth yeah i have to tattoos too um
i've got uh meditation and concentration
i got to know thyself here
um so yeah tattooing is a good way to
create the
talismanic reminders of what you're
committing yourself to
um but so that the way the idea of truth
um there because let's zero in on a term
that sort of bridges i think this notion
of realization when people realize
things which is both the like you said
those ah-ha moments
but also the way in which their own
bodies and the world is disclosed to
them in a new pattern
and then it's that new pattern that
affords them
transforming how they're moving how
they're moving how they're even
inhabiting their bodies
and and you've given me several examples
which i
i would i'm asking i'm requesting that
you would share one of those examples
of how you've gone in there's somebody
and they're trying to correct
their movement right like you did the
example of somebody who's sprinting
you've done examples of
you've given me several examples and i
found each one really tasty
right and then what you did is the way
in which you you found that
you know the mujust you found you found
the analogy
that you know bridges between the
propositional the perspectival
and it affords that aha realization
and an affordance opens up for them and
then they start to move
in a new way and it's very different
from them knowing that they need to move
in a new way
like you say just practicing there's
something that you did that transforms
right their perspectival knowing so they
start to inhabit the world
and their body in a different way and
and that and so it's
the language borders on like on one hand
on like
on poetry on one side and it's almost
like magic
right in in on the other side because
it's actually sort of making something
possible for people
first of all is that a fair description
of oh no
completely completely it's i know
exactly what you're talking about
and i have i think uh a good example for
which we can
we might be able to go through others in
a different angle
but let me use a simple one that
everyone can relate to and i think i've
shared the one
of my son learning to ride his bike i
think this one probably
more than the others eloquently
articulates what you're describing there
and so it's a long story so i'm going to
share the latter half
it goes something like this during the
covet period
my son was learning to ride his bike and
as he was learning to ride his bike i
find as someone who studies learning
quite literally professionally that
understanding how and why learning takes
place becomes quite important to me and
so
these are beautiful natural time points
as a parent
to see in action and also often times
see where you are miserably wrong at
least wrong
and so it got me thinking about
what what underpins learning
which is to say why do we need coaches
you know you alluded to i was able to
use
language to intervene to positively
disrupt
i might say yeah and allow for a new
reorganization that this person desired
but we also know that people learn
things all the time
without coaches without teachers some
people might say that's where the
greatest learning takes place and so
for me i've just been thinking about
well why do we need
coaches and by no means am i saying this
is 100 accurate but at least
pragmatically
i've started to observe that four
conditions
if met allow learning and here i'm
talking about movement learning
but i do believe this transcends
movement that four conditions if
if set learning will occur call it
naturally
but certain disruptions with these
conditions
without intervention might either result
in the
neutralization or the flatlining of
progress
so i stay the way i am and for for an
elite person that might be great
but in other instances right if you
don't use it you lose it
if i stop engaging with the practice i
start to see erosion
and so the four preconditions for
learning for me were the following
one there needs to be a clear goal it
needs to be
salient at some level it doesn't need to
be salient
at the propositional level it's not like
that the four or five-year-old needs to
be able to clearly articulate
the goal of riding a bike but the goal
still needs to be self-evident to them
from a perceptual perspective so it
needs to be a goal uh
number two there needs to be a a
feedback loop
meaning there needs to be immediate
feedback that is
obvious again that is salient to the
learner
third piece is there has to be a desire
there needs to be a desire to achieve
the goal
if there is no desire there's nothing
motivating the pursuit and the practice
so it's not likely to begin and then the
fourth and final one
is they need to have the capability
of achieving this skill and so my son
for example when riding the bike
he would literally have to be tall
enough and strong enough to pedal the
bike
if those preconditions were not met it
doesn't matter if the goal is clear the
feedback is there and the desire is
strong
and so i think you could extend these
four conditions to other things
but here we are he's learning to ride
his bike and sure enough early on
he's he's coaching me he's like dad let
me go
hold on let go push faster he's
orchestrating the whole thing
and so fine he learns the training
wheels come off
happy days the goal is clear in my case
he wants to beat his sister on the walk
so he wants to be sister this thing
needs to not fall over so the goal is
quite clear
he has a desire to beat his sister
around the block
and the feedback well well gravity is a
heck of a teacher
yeah and he had finally matured to a
physical stature he could ride the bike
so four preconditions are there happy
days he's learning
on his own he's coaching me more than
i'm coaching him
but we then reach a critical juncture
whereby
when he tries to speed up he's over
correcting with his handlebars causing
him to swerve
and fall now i allow him to
work through this but i start to notice
something
in the morning he's not as excited to
get on the bike
right right right he's not his he's not
as quick he in fact might even push
back oh hey buddy you want to go ride
yeah okay
and so what do i start to notice oh well
i start to draw a possible correlation
between him reaching this this
this progress gap and
his motivation his desire and so that as
a coach
brings in an interesting point when
failure reaches a certain level
and frustration follows we start to
possibly see a reduction in desire
and so it's not that the goal is gone
still there
gravity hasn't gone anywhere and he
hasn't lost his strength overnight
so in his case i saw it as desire so i
said okay so my my job now
is to go in and see if i can
in in provoke desire but not
by motivating him because that wasn't
working john i said hey come on buddy
did not work okay i'm scratching my head
well how do we do this
i can't change the goal ah feedback
what he's suffering from is he's not
aware of the feature of his environment
that contains the information needed
to make the progress towards his goal
that he desires
okay okay where's that information
the information for me was in his
handlebars the motion of his handlebars
is what was ultimately causing the thing
that was causing his desire to erode
and so i step in now we're a musical
family
and i i gave him a very simple question
i said madden
show me what your handlebars are doing
when they're loud
and he kind of looked at me and he moved
his handlebars very very quickly
in a big exaggerated motion and i said
show me what your handlebars are doing
when they're quiet
and all of a sudden he stopped and he
held him still very proud of himself
i said okay now when you're speeding up
to catch your sister
do you think you should keep your
handlebars loud or quiet
he looked at me the victim said quiet so
he's four
right and he's getting the analogy he's
getting
the comparison right all the while what
i'm doing is i'm drawing his attention
to the handlebars right but i'm doing
i'm doing it in a way
where the handlebars don't become all
consuming
they don't become the only focus i
believe you use the term they become a
soft
focus the background rather than the
foreground
and so now we created a very simple
mechanism
for when he was writing to either you
know affirmed himself
keep it quiet or for dad to say or mom
to say
keep it quiet and i'm not saying this is
the only reason
but within a few days he was speeding
past his sister
uphill down the hills and he was
corrected and in that
example i find the heart of
of coaching really it's knowing when to
step
in it's knowing what we are stepping
into in terms of the change
but then here's the kicker it's knowing
how yeah
yeah how to generate the change such
that the learner
feels that they're almost the author of
it so
that that was beautifully set that was
beautifully said
and so can we zero in now
on like i want to really zero in on like
this
this this that you know i i get it
there's this kairos right you
you're sensing like when's the time to
intervene and
what's the context of the intervention
you really have to sensitize yourself to
that
the greeks had a great word for this
they have two words for wisdom one is
sophia the other is from
and from this is exactly that wisdom of
like when should i intervene and
what's going on here you know that
contextual sensitivity that
gives you the optimal point of
intervention right the finesse
that pascal talked about right like that
so that's
but that's continuous like it's not like
although i'm using two words but that
that zeroing in
and the intervention it seems to me like
it's it it's
like it's continuous or at least it's in
dialogue with this process
of an emerging right analogy of an
emerging
and it's more than just i i granted
you use the word analogy and it's fine
but i i i want to say that
it's something more like it's like it's
an enacted analogy it's almost like
it's it's not this but it's like what
people are doing when they're doing a
ritual
in a religious practice right they're
not just they're not just thinking of an
analogy
they're enacting it and they're enacting
it by committing themselves to a process
of transformation within it
right and so you have to get you have to
you have to get that you know the
phronesis
of the kairos and then you have to come
up with the analogy
that the per that's going to catch the
person that they're going to internalize
right that they're going to enact right
and they're going to commit themselves
to
and i mean so there's an amazing art
there and so
i'm just like
it seems to me like you've zeroed in
on how this language this
this i wish i had a better term but the
enacted analogies
right how they are bridging
between the propositional the procedural
and the perspective
like you're it's clear to your son your
son had the pieces
right like because soon as you asked him
he he knew
he knew but there was it was almost like
you know there's there's the
the like metaphor bridging it's almost
like the connection
what you did is right he's got this he's
got this and this and this and then
it's almost like we talked about in the
cognitive science literature
you did problem finding you found the
you found the problem of
you know how to connect these things
that are not yet connected
and then you gave him an enacted analogy
that somehow puts the procedural and the
perspective on the proposition
altogether
in a way and he can commit himself to it
right away
and so the interesting thing for me is
like again i know i've asked you this
before and it's an unfair question
it's an unfair question but it's a
question between friends and so it's
it's it's more of an invitation to more
conversations
like how do you do that like what's
going on i mean
uh right uh because i think and and to
be fair to me
not and i'm not trying to put you in a i
like you a lot i'm not trying to put you
in a heart
a bad spot but you did say and so
i'm calling to you on that you know you
want to transfer this you want to you
want to learn how to take this
and make it available for responding to
the meeting crisis so this is
to my mind like the key question and
again this is a socratic question i
don't i don't expect people to say well
here it is here's the algorithm
but maybe by getting into discussion we
can induce we can draw out
so i think we started to get into uh to
the schema
i i am starting to formulate and it's
in the book so so it is a first it is a
first attempt
and so so a number of things here i want
to kind of start
at one thousand of you that will go to
the hundreds of you
yeah and so the thousand foot view i
actually believe it was during
our our panel discussion it was one
thing that i know that
stood out in my mind because i never
said it before which is why i love these
kind of dynamic
audio complications for me that the flow
state that emerges allows some of the
best
thinking and code generation but
what i said there is is analogies
almost by their very nature allow you to
collaborate
with your former selves yeah yeah i like
i liked i i really
liked that that that linkage to
aspiration
right and and distributed cognition
across time
yeah exactly and the reason i
thought of that again by analogy
is because when people said well why you
know many people write a book
and they say he'll never do it again but
when people say well i do it again i'm
like i will do it for the rest of my
life
right exactly they're like why why
i'm like because i realized writing
allows me to collaborate with myself
every time i finish uh a draft
and i set it down and i go away for a
couple weeks and i come back
i'm like what was i thinking it's almost
like i'm reading someone else's book
yeah but
each time i went back i found the voice
was getting
closer and closer to the one i wanted
the one i was aspiring towards
and so that thought was already floating
in my mind so when we're on the panel
like holy smokes
that's why that's what analogies are
they're a collaboration
because analogy right it's a comparison
between something you're
familiar with and usually something
you're less familiar with
not that you you can form analogies
between two familiar things but normally
in a teaching context i use an analogy
because i think
the thing i'm gonna say is something
you're familiar with
and i'm gonna take your knowledge of
that familiarity and your implicit
understanding of that thing and i'm
going to map it onto this thing you're
not familiar with
and with that you carry the knowledge
the structure the schema so
one i've used last time we spoke an
analogy we use in sprinting
we've all seen people sprint the person
that kind of looks hunched over when
they're running almost falls on their
face
right no we use the analogy of when you
get off the line
and for people watching listening
imagine usain bolt you know
gun goes off bam and he sprints forward
we say
drive off the line like a jet taking off
now
nobody consumes that analogy and says
i am now physically my matter has
changed into a jet
but are there are there characteristics
that we can map
well low to high is a is a
characteristic of motion
a very fast characteristic of motion
a strong position from toe to tail
right or from nose to tail and from head
to toe right so strong
and so there's all these features that
we can map over
and so for me very early on it's this
idea of
feature mapping and we talked that we
talked about
deidre gentner yeah
structure structure mapping her work
really inspired a lot of my own so you
ask
how do i go about generating analogies
and you're not the only one to ask this
question
i i get asked it all the time and i try
to tell people to be very clear
that this is not something that i feel i
was naturally
attuned for okay i i would not say if i
go back and look at the
the nick 12 years ago was i using
analogies
as fluently as i am now as quickly
as i am not even close and so something
happened
the first thing that happened is i
recognized
right the invisible became visible i
recognized that language was important
and this specific attribute
feature of language that we call analogy
seems to be
exceptionally important right right
the way i would argue that if you listen
if you recorded a conversation between
yourself and a five-year-old
a 15 year old a 25 year old and a 50
year old
that obviously the concepts you were
talking about are different but if we
just look at the structure of your
language
i'd argue that the analogy used
and the kind of analogy use you are
using is going to be very different and
it's likely to be different
based on the age of the person thus only
using analogies that they have
experiences they could relate to
and obviously analogies that you feel
will somehow connect to them
as an individual independent of their
age and so
i started to notice this and at first
it was like brute force let me just let
me try to generate more
but i kept running into these blockages
and so when you're when you're coaching
professional athletes you can't sit
there and say hey can i have a 10 minute
intermission
to come up with some better cues to give
you that you can move faster over 10
10 yards not going to happen and so let
me fast forward
to today where i got to and so it
started with
deidre gentner's work and she talks
about from a mapping perspective let's
stick with my analogy
because hopefully people can visualize
the sprinting and a jet taking off
right right right he talks about two
things being mapped
we map actions and we
map attributes yeah and so generally
speaking the way
in reading her work i took this in a
movement context
and this is where john i i feel we're
within this conversation and the ones
that will follow
we can start to then transcend movement
and bring this analogy into
the world of concepts beyond movement
but actions and attributes
actions i took that as dynamic it's a
feature of the movement
that if my leg can be in position a and
b
i'm looking at how it moves from a to b
that's what we're going to call
action and an attribute is something
more
a static it's a feature of the body so
if i was to make the analogy
during a push-up keep your back flat
like a table
i'm taking static flatness of a table
and i'm mapping it on to what should be
the static flatness
of your back in a push-up that's an
attribute but if i say
when you change direction explode off
the ground
like a bouncy ball off the ground i'm
invoking something of more of an
action there's a speed motion element to
it
and so what i started to realize is okay
when i'm coaching
i need to identify is the thing i'm
trying to change
categorically a action
a dynamic motion or
is it an attribute so is it an attribute
of the body
they're flexed and they should be
neutral or
an action their leg needs to come up
faster than it is right now
once i've identified that then i can say
okay that means i've identified the
thing that i need to change
now how do i go about doing that i have
to identify an analogy
using language using experiences they
are
familiar with and so to summarize the
schema
if i can identify the feature of the
movement
and make sure the feature of the
movement is similar to the thing i'm
analogizing it against
and that the thing i'm analogizing it
against is familiar
right to you john you know this
reference i'm making you know about
you've seen a jet take off
you've presumably seen a table so sprint
like a jet taking off
lands with you if we look at that then
that starts to generate
if you would an engine for pulling on
all the things that they're familiar
with that have this attribute or all the
things they're familiar with
that have this action in its simplest
level
that's how i approach it that's
fantastic that's
very uh your talent for exploitation is
uh very much appreciated by me um so
i mean i'm also very familiar with
gentner's work i teach it and one of the
courses i teach on thinking and
reasoning
i've done work on metaphor a lot of work
on metaphor analogy
so i i want to bring those things to it
and see if that
will enrich the discussion uh so gentner
um uh also talks about well
before we go to gentner let's go to our
tony uh or tony has the uh a salience
imbalance theory
of metaphor every theory of metaphor
ultimately fails from counter examples
so you can't
none of these theories will be
definitional but they're all helpful
they're all helpful
and so what ortoni says is uh so uh
you know here's here's the target of the
metaphor this is
what i want to understand and here's the
vehicle of the metaphor what i
what i'm familiar with and i'm going to
transfer from the vehicle to the target
just so we have some language to talk
about
and then what he says is what what you
do is you find a feature
in the vehicle that is highly that is
regularly salient
for the vehicle and then what you do is
you map it on to a feature that is
regularly not salient for the target
so you find a salience imbalance and
then by doing that mapping what you're
actually doing
i would say is you that's why it's like
an aha experience
you're altering what you find salient
and thereby what you find relevant
and so it seems to me that one of the
things you have to do
is you like i'm trying to make sense of
you something
like he had this information but it
wasn't salient to him
and then you used and then use the
feature of music that's very sailing to
music it's loud or it's soft
and then what that did is it took this
non-salient feature
and made it more salient so that sounds
like it plugs into your
example the salience imbalance
absolutely going in the next edition i
love that you're 100 right
otherwise they would have changed it
themselves yeah exactly
exactly exactly so it's it's it's it's
like when you have an inside experience
the information's available to you
like the nine dot you know problem well
you always knew that there was space
outside the nine dots
but it wasn't salient to you wasn't
relevant to you right away and so
now bringing in an idea from getting her
so gentner talks a lot about
like she has she has a sort of a
step-by-step
decision tree for how you decide what to
map
and she says you you map like you map
you prefer relations over uh single
features
and you you prefer systems of relations
over
single relations so that's why we like
uh
that the the you know the atom is a
solar system uh because we can map
not only can we map a bunch of relations
we can map a relation between all the
relations
she calls that systematicity and so it's
it seems to me
that what's also going on in your
selection and and
the artistry of it and i mean that as a
compliment by the way the artist
is that you're trying to find not just
the features but you're trying to find
the structural functional organization
of the features
that will so one of the things the
metaphor does the analogy does
it's not just giving them a feature list
it's like i mean your work like
it's giving them a feature schema it's
giving them
right not only the features but implicit
in the analogy
is how the features are all fitted
together and are working
together so for example you've got the
feature of acceleration
and a slow thing but you could you could
you you know you might give
you might you might have one thing that
has one other like a rocket
but it doesn't have the other feature
right and right you have to have
something that they put
that that sort of gestalts them together
so that
there's that systematicity there's a
there's a structural functional relation
and i'm i'm wondering if um
if if what happens is do you get
like are there some cis are there some
situ like i'm
i'm asking a calibration question sorry
yeah yeah
the idea is let's say like the more
comprehensive
and dynamically complex the needed
intervention do you
find that the metaphor is
correspondingly has sort of a richer
systematicity to it
that it like you feel that the the
metaphor is sort of
richer or denser uh a metaphor
i i i don't i i'd have to think about
that that that
that description of it has not crossed
my mind from the standpoint of
the use of of metaphor or analogy for
a complex versus let's say a less
complex problem right
right in fact what i find is the more
complex the problem
the the easier it is to find an
aha yeah buy a metaphor
because and i kind of call this the
trojan horse effect
right you talk about all the implicit
meaning i can
hide i can hide a ton
of implicit meaning and a ton of
relational meaning
inside of an analogy but if i was to
unpack that
and make it explicit to to to allow
the warriors out of the trojan horse so
to speak
then it would dominate it would create
chaos in my mind i get it ultimately
leading the metaphor
ineffectual if i can
highlight something that that you said
earlier because i think it it'll add
brightness to it you talked about this
salience imbalance which i love
and just to put in my own words the so
to speak that the vehicle the thing that
they are familiar with
that i'm mapping on to the target the
thing i'm trying to teach them
or change i like the primacy of the
vehicle
is that that the thing part of it that i
need them to be aware of is obvious it's
inherent inside of it
yeah yeah and the thing i'm trying to
change which has a similarity
is not so that's salience i love that
what i find though inside of that is the
more the two things i'm comparing
map on to each other and and gentler
talks about this
the less the less impactful
because that that one
let's say salient feature that i really
want to stand out
in the vehicle that i really want to
stand out in the analogy
sometimes can be dampened by all the
other points of familiarity
and so they can't find it and so let me
actually
give an example that's the first time
i've said this the
the sprint like a jet taking off right
right by itself
oftentimes is
ineffective right right here's why the
here's why in my
opinion i just want to say you're really
asking you're really answering the
question about calibration that i asked
oh okay you really are just go just go
yeah
so the reason the jet is ineffective
is because there are too many obvious
features
that map onto sprinting you can talk
about it's
fast you can talk about again from
from you know nose to tail it needs to
be straight
well if you look at the side of the body
it needs to be straight so there's a lot
so it's almost like when there's a lot
of features that map onto each other
the person abandons ship conceptually
because they don't one doesn't stand out
so i always
i oh like you get a bag of peanuts right
maybe not anymore but i give them a bag
of peanuts as well on this jet
i say listen i need you to explode off
the line like a jet taking off
gradually rising so i try to bring them
to the salient
of the gradual rise of the jet
and that's the piece i want them to map
over let me give an example of an
analogy
that the salience is obvious like you
don't it doesn't need any
translation because what i did there
were some analogies there's a bit of
translation
this one doesn't require if i say i want
you to line up
for your sprint okay and you have to
imagine i used to work in phoenix
arizona so desert landscape
context will allow this analogy to make
more sense right right right
i want you to imagine there is a
rattlesnake
two feet behind you reared up
ready to bite your calf
i need you to beat the bite beat the
bunt
and so again inherent inside of that
the i'm almost making explicit
the comparison but i think what we're
revealing
with analogy as well is the benefit of
collaborating with a former state
is the the knowledge of what getting off
the line fast that's great
but what does the analogy also give me
it gives me an emotional
quality right there's
there's a sense embedded in that analogy
of
how to do this i'm not just gradually
getting off the line
i literally am getting off the line like
my life depends on it
and so it's not only brightening the
technique
it's brightening the the the energy the
heartbeat of the temperature
and so much of movement so much of
movement
has a feel has an emotional quality you
talk to athletes
they talk about feeling in the way
energy fluxes yet so much of our
language
in coaching lacks that emotional quality
we say
extend this push that rotate there
but that as if that's enough it's not
sufficient
to actually help someone wholesale
embody a change
so that's really interesting that's
powerful uh
so so there is a kind of
there is a kind of logos there there is
a structural functional organization but
what you did was really interesting you
said it's actually
not so much just between features but
also between
sort of different aspects or functions
of cognition
are all you're also organizing them with
the analogy so you're getting the
person's
right knowledge of how to you know move
their body
but you that what what the thing the me
the analogy is doing is actually putting
them into an emotional state
it's giving them a perspective and a
motivation right
that's fantastic that's really good
that's really really interesting
so i just want to pick up on
another point that was touched on
briefly and this is some of the work
i've done and
my colleague dan chappie has done
experimental work on
so you don't you don't really i mean
people talk about metaphorical truth
it's more like
it's truth more like in the sense of
allothea a metaphor is true to or
analogy is true to the greek which it
brings about a transformation
that connects you to the world in a
better way right um
it's not true the way like f you know
force equals mass times acceleration
or something like that but so but what
what you do evaluate
metaphors on so so the thing that stands
in for is it true or false because we're
actually talking about transformation
not not possession of proposition right
what stands in for truth is what's
called aptness
like if how apt a metaphor is
and what's interesting about uh the
aptness of a metaphor and i want to see
if this translates back to your
experience
so and there's experimental work showing
this and you brought it up with
you know gettinger's point and other
people have noted it
you know if the vehicle and the tenor
are too similar
you get all these mappings but as you
said you don't know which one is the
simulator or the relevant one
and so yeah so let me give you there's
an example i use it
for my own work in my lectures uh if if
the tenor
if the target in the vehicle are too
similar
you don't get a you don't get a great
metaphor even though you're getting tons
of mapping
so if i say to you bees are hornets you
don't go wow
that's such a great metaphor let's look
at all the mappings in it because
because so many things are familiar you
don't know
how to reorganize what you find salient
so that's
and then on the other extreme is if
they're if they're too different
the identity becomes so abstract
that it you're it's vague about what the
transformation is going to be
well when i say to you well you know
arguments are chairs
because they're both human-made and
they're structures that support
isn't that a great metaphor and you go
what that what like what
what what about chairs right and so and
so people don't like either one of those
extremes
and so this aptness you've got to get
what's there's a duality to it
you have to you have to
right you have to get
both a relevant difference and that's
backgrounded and then a relevant
sameness
that's foregrounded did that did did
that make did that make sense
well my slight deviation in uh in
eyes here is because i want to make a
connection that i feel
is is right into your episode 12.
you went through this whole idea of
you know trustworthiness something
elegant doesn't make it fluid
is it trivial is it far-fetched exactly
yeah i think when you said you know when
something is uh let's see here
profound is like there's this
optimization of it's trustworthy
it's it's elegant in its in in its
simplicity to explain
but it's fluent right we don't have to
take no energy
to understand it and almost for me that
that profound
sense that ah ha it is this i i can
trust it
it's elegant in its simplicity and it
seems to be
fluid it takes it takes no effort to be
to be brought on board i don't know as
you're talking
that no no that's good yeah yeah yeah
yeah no i like this
oh that yeah okay so the idea is
right there there's so coming from the
front coming from the
vehicle there's a lot of familiar lines
and then they converge on the needed
thing the central thing and then that is
the nexus point that's the point that
gives you maximal intervention
right and when you write oh that's good
that's really good and you have to
you have to strike oh i like that i
hadn't put that together
nick that's brilliant i didn't quit
quickly but i knew you yeah because when
you went through
what makes something you know uh trivial
a lot of convergence with no elegance
you know far fetched elegance
with little convergence my mind's like
okay he is starting to ex
because for me i'm nearly obsessed with
how to be a better thinker you know in a
world of noise
how do we find signal yeah but almost as
an analogy that's what we're talking
about
how can we communicate in a way to
brighten the right signals
that's what good metaphor is about so so
yeah and i i even use metaphors when i'm
talking about this
because i talk about the elegance of a
construct as being multi-opt
right because it maps into many
different uh
many different domains but that's really
good i like that so the idea is
that what i'm looking for is a
maybe we can put the two things together
a good analogy
is one that's going to generate that
plausibility
right uh in a powerful way um
and and it's going to cause a salient a
a a significant restructuring of the
salience of
of the target is that that's sort of the
aha
that's sort of yeah a generated
plausibility that generates a
on aha because of right so you tr
the trustworthiness makes you trust the
the salience imbalance right and and
change how you think about something
but the elegance is what gives you the
sense of it empowering you
so that's really good i hadn't thought
about that those that putting those two
together i think is very helpful
yeah yeah no for me it's you know i find
so so much of this hangs on their
their deep familiarity with
the vehicle yeah so
i i'm i'm working with uh you know an
athlete right now
who has been been trying to solve a
movement
problem he just so happens to work in
golf and he's been working at this for a
long time
right and so what we've done
and this is almost uh how do we
mechanize this
again in movement coaching but also you
know i think there's there's
therapeutic exemplars for using metaphor
metaphor and analogy to kind of
transcend your circumstances to listen
to the words we are using the you know
i'm underwater you know
trained to the ground whatever it might
be so almost i was trying to
to steal a little bit of that intellect
into this process and so
my steps with him have been as follows
step one
before we can even talk about analogy or
metaphor generation
we need to clearly understand that the
feature
that it we're trying to target the
feature that we are trying to change
a lot of time with him let's unpack in
your movement
what needs to change right and so that's
taken a couple conversations and even
for for the individual for them to try
to unpack it because
they've been of many minds but once we
nailed it
then it was a very simple task i said
okay
what visual
and this is an analogy what visual
can you can occupy your mind
that you feel by its very nature
would force upon a change right and i'm
very clear when i say this
and i i don't want you to feel the
change is one of intellectual knowing
that okay these things propositionally
go together if i think this that should
happen no
that when you think of this thing you
feel
the change right right right right get
it i got it
okay and so i look at that as they
download
the implicit meaning of the analogy
on contact right it takes no effort it's
completely fluent
in many cases with maybe a little bit of
translation and so
basically i armed him with the the
schema
so to speak and after a couple sessions
guess what he found it he found one and
and now it's a matter of grooving it in
now i'm not saying it's perfect we might
have to pivot a little bit but we are
we are building the analogy
right why do i say we're building the
analogy because
if i am golfing i am golfing that that's
the skill i can't transcend that
i'm swinging a club and hitting a ball
yeah so
to to transcend that and thus bring
something new to it
it's not like i can change the rules of
the game either
right right right i can't bring anything
outside of me
ah but i have this virtual thing where i
can
move as if right right right the big
thing
if i move as if i feel this if i move as
if i
were there on a cliff let's say all of a
sudden
my movement organizes differently and so
for me this is this is kind of that that
process that we go through
and so oftentimes an analogy isn't a one
and done
for me early on that was the case but
now i talked about
a working analogy yeah yeah
it's like like almost like i saw it
that's what i was trying to convey with
the poetry of it
yeah yeah right it keeps building yeah
yeah
yeah and even the the even if we abandon
the the structure of an analogy which is
to say it's words
oftentimes we still contain the meaning
and we transfer the meaning
to a different structure which might be
a comparison that is more salient a
comparison
that they are more familiar with that
they like better
and so for example i might say to an
individual
when they're sprinting hey i want you to
explode off the ground like you're
sprinting up a set of stairs
and so the meaning i'm trying to convey
is more push into the ground
with upward forward propulsion but let's
say that's not working for them
but i haven't they understand what i'm
trying to convey
but it's not affecting them the analogy
isn't working
on them and so now let's say i change
okay instead of sprinting up
stairs imagine you're sprinting up a
hill
right okay it's still
forward upward propulsion but it's a
different visual context
so i have some people the hill
absolutely lights them up they get it it
works
instant change other people it's the
stairs right right
right as long as we get the meaning
right the
the wrapping the coat of paint the words
the exemplar we use
to contain that meaning that can change
and so that's
a deeper way to suggest how i think
about
a working analogy once we get the
meaning right
then we just got to find the packaging
to get it to hit
so i noticed that um like
when you're explaining a lot of these
examples the movement
seems to be like that you put people
you trigger their perspectival knowing
and even some participatory knowing
right and then that's what you're using
to try and train
uh like you know transform the
procedural knowing like when you said
you know swing your golf club as if
you're standing on
a cliff right like i got you get you
immediately get the perspective
right and then all all the implicit
right for in that perspective
right what right and then you you bought
you start to assume a particular
identity
you embody right and then that sort of
triggers which skill set
is going to be available to you is it
like
is it or even like even like you said
when you're doing push-ups
you said you know you're basically
telling the person be it
be a table and what would it be like to
be a table kind of thing right
uh there's so there's a process of
identification
that's going on a perspectival
transformation nick are you still there
i am here yes yeah you're frozen there
for a sec
uh just wanted to make sure so i mean is
that is that
is that prototypical are you almost
always
like uh like putting people into a
particular
identity within a particular perspective
and then they use that to transform
uh the procedural knowing it is
a hundred percent so so here let's take
your cliff
example you you you unlock something
there
i'm always interested when people say
implicit knowing right
it's it's knowing without telling i even
though i conceptually understand that
i still struggle with this goal how can
you know something
if you can't verbalize it well you know
you can enact it you can act it out you
can
move as if yeah and so take the cliff
example
the cliff example where does the
information come from well the
information comes from as you said
yourself
that direct perception right you are
able to
almost embody an act in the mind if i
were on a cliff
there are certain things i could not
would not do
you know i would not want to lean back
i probably am going to have more of a
forward-shifted
posture i might even be aware of the
wind so it might stiffen me up through
the middle
and these are not things that i have to
propositionally think about
these are things that i instantly feel
and this is that this is that pursuit we
use
words to the degree that they get you
the feeling
and so what you've said there is we use
language
to literally cue to cue a memory state
that allows you to step into that memory
state and say
what would it be like yes answering and
answering
what would it be like that's all the
information
i need you to carry into the present
environment
and that by definition for me would be
the implicit
knowing the feeling you appropriate
from the analogy into the present world
you turn
virtual into the real that's very very
powerful that's very very
very powerful so so this th this enacted
poetry
i like that better than an active
analogy because it because poesis means
making
right right yeah so so this
this enacted poesis right uh maybe
that's even better
because it captures all of those
different things i wanted to say earlier
in one term
so this enacted poesis it's really a
powerful way
right of of getting people to
like instead of top down from their
proposition they're going sort of bottom
up from
the identities they assume the agent
arena identities within a particular
perspective of knowing
and then that shifts the the the the
skills that they're trying to acquire or
the skills that they're trying to
transform
it reminds me of some of the work i've
been doing the dan chappie about how
people
the scientists using the rover on mars
and they they have to go through this
process of identifying with the rover
and then that gives them the ability to
like look at the pictures and see as if
they're on mars and then they can do the
field work
they right um which is really really
really really interesting thing
so we're almost done for today so i just
wanted to lay some seeds for our next
conversation because i want i wanted
this to
progress through a series uh i invite
you to to join me on that
that journey um so i mean there's a lot
here
that you know has potential resonance
uh you know with what people have been
doing and i mentioned it much earlier
within really
you know within religious ritual right
you people go in
what would it be like to be you know you
know the son of god right
what would it be like and then you and
you you know you ident you know
it is not i but christ who lives in me
you know there's paul and he's assuming
that identity and
he's trying to adopt the perspective and
that's that's what's actually helping
him
to transform his skills and his virtues
so i can see a lot of people listening
to what we're talking about who might
have some kind of religious
background going yeah and and finding
right uh
a bridging there or and other people who
who might be but be hearing it and it
might
it might be sort of the obverse of that
they might be saying
the thing they're talking about that
ability that's something i've been
hungering for
but not in movement or in sport i've
been hungry for that more
comprehensively
and so putting those two together you
see where i'm going with this
there's a way in which what we're
talking about here is deeply pregnant
with this
general issue of
enabling people and there's a metaphor
right in the title to awaken from
the meeting crisis and what i what i'd
like to do is
follow this up and i know you have you
know uh
you know broader philosophical points to
make about this you know
we've talked about the way you've been
thinking about you know challenging the
cartesian framework and what that means
um and so i want to invite you to come
back and build upon what we've been
talking about
here today and you know build it out
into those larger
uh cognitive cultural issues so that i
think that's what we could do next time
together
yeah no i i think that's spot on because
since our last discussion you know for
me
it has been asking the question okay how
can we extend
this approach and let's be clear
this is not the first nor the last time
people will talk about the benefit and
the use of metaphor
for many many different reasons
allowing it to be more accessible more
more visible more mainstream
is what i see this this journey being so
important for but nick you are bringing
something important to it
you're bringing like i've read a lot of
the literature on metaphor
but you're bringing the you're bringing
the four e cog cyan you're bringing the
embodied
enacted aspect and the distributed
cognition
you're bringing the embodiment the
embeddedness the enactedness and the
extendedness
of metaphor that is not talked about in
a lot of the literature of metaphor
oh well i i and see i don't even know i
was doing that which is why
i've always said this to people when i
email uh a professor or intellectual
or whoever the the thing i tend to open
up with is you have
answers to questions you've never
asked and i guess that's what i hope
here is that i have answers
to questions you've never and vice versa
and so i'm excited
to your your guidance here to see how we
can yes i think the word is extend
yeah work well beyond because you know
in our conversations for me personally
that's my own journey so i'm excited to
start uh let's say
parlaying this beyond movement so
that'll be a fun next chat
great so i look forward to that we'll
we'll set it up and schedule it and
we'll release this as as a series uh so
nick this has been wonderful uh like
again i'm always
um i get entranced by like when you
when when the passion takes you the
their fire is there and then
and then you know your explication and
explanation of what you do
it just it starts to flow it's it's
really wonderful there's an aesthetic
quality to it
that's that's deeply pleasing and it
affords engagement
so i want to thank you for for being
here and for
uh like i said i'm glad you're going to
come back i'm going to continue on
uh this discussion about uh about
you know enacted poesis because i think
it's really really important
it's really really cool the feelings are
mutual thank you john